Okay טוב. tov. Today's דף, daf, officially it's 74, we're behind we
pick up on 73 עין גמל עמוד אלף Ayin Gimmel Amud Aleph
near the bottom and it's we pick up with
אמר ליה רבא להנהו דמנטרי באגי. Amar lei Rava l'hanei d'mantrei bagi.
The line starts with the word באגי. bagi. It is about 12
lines from the bottom of עין גמל עמוד אלף. Ayin Gimmel Amud
Aleph.
So Rava said to the people that basically watched
the valleys where the wheat was growing,
they were the watchmen. But the story was was that they didn't
get paid until the harvest came in. But their job of
watching stopped before they ended a while before their actual payment because
it wasn't just when the wheat was cut, it was when it
was cut and threshed and came to market. That's when the owners
had money to pay them. Okay? So essentially therefore they are accepting
deferred payment for their service. And what the owners used to do
is they used to throw in a little extra. Okay? They really
per hour they should have been getting
$1,200 but I'm going to pay you two months from now I'll
give you $1,300.
So here's a ריבית ribbis problem. So here's what Rava said to
them.
The word starts with באגי. bagi. It's עין גמל עמוד אלף. Ayin
Gimmel Amud Aleph.
Yeah, like 11 lines from the bottom. Okay, אמר ליה רבא להנהו
דמנטרי באגי. Amar lei Rava l'hanei d'mantrei bagi. פוקו הפיכו בהדי דרי.
Puku hafichu b'hadei dari. Go out,
help a little bit in the threshing floor, turn over the grain.
And
therefore your service and
your fee for your service, your service won't be done until until
the threshing is done. Still do a little trivial nominal work for
the owner until the point where he's going to actually pay you.
Okay? Why? דשכר אינו משתלם אלא
לבסוף. D'sechar eino mishtalem ela l'vasof. Because payment for service is only
paid at the end of the services.
And at that time when they're paying, so therefore since your service
is only going to be
done like two months from now when the owners are ready to
pay you, then they're not giving you extra money for the fact
that you waited because we're going to like nominally make it as
if you're continuing to work until that point. Now there's another problem.
Okay, fine. So I dropped by once every few weeks and I
spent ten minutes there. So officially I was still working until everything
was done. But nevertheless he gave me an extra hundred dollars. The
extra work I did during that two-month period when I was waiting
was not worth an extra hundred dollars. So that's the last phrase
where it says אזולי הוא דקא מוזיל גבייכו. Azulei hu d'ka mozil
gabaichu. He's just like literally it means he's selling things cheaply, but
what it means is like if he's giving you grain and he's
giving you a little bit more than you deserve, he's just giving
you the grain at a cheap rate. Meaning once you are your
שכר sechar is at end at that time, if he wants to
overpay you, that's his business. If he wants to give you more
wheat than maybe your service deserves and therefore it's like he's selling
you the wheat cheaply, whatever, that's his business. But at least we
framed it so there was no postponement of payment. Once there's a
postponement of payment and he gives you more than you deserve, that's
a type of a ריבית. ribbis. But because you worked up to
that point even in a nominal fashion, then if he gave you
more than you deserve it's still not a ריבית. ribbis. It's not
for postponement of payment. He's just being generous. Okay? So that's what
you have to do. Keep on working in a nominal way until
the time of payment until he's ready to pay you. And then
if he wants to be overly generous, that's his business. But if
you stopped working two months ago, then his then that's a type
of a ריבית ribbis that he's giving you extra. Yes, Charlie?
Why can they ever permit to delay payment? Exactly, you can't be
paid, you can't buy a car with monthly payments for two years?
Right, right. So
Charlie's asking a different issue. Charlie's asking the issue of הלנת שכר
שכיר. halanat sechar sachir. Okay, but you can make an arrangement with
the owner. Okay? That's only when you can arrange to get paid
at a later date. It does raise an interesting question, which is
why people wouldn't regularly take advantage of that. Like if it's a
buyer's market,
if you need the work, why don't I just pre-arrange with you
that you're going to be
paid at a much later time rather than when I owe you
the money back? But anyway, but yes, it is true and we're
going to get to that later in this מסכת masechet that there's
an איסור issur of הלנת שכר שכיר. halanat sechar sachir. But this
can be done with a contractual arrangement. Yeah.
So is that different than deferred than ultimately you don't pay for
the whole you pay in installments?
Right. And then if you pay extra because you're paying in installments,
that's known as ריבית. ribbis.
You cannot buy an automobile with monthly payments over two months
unless it's from a non-Jew. But from a Jew and that you're
it's due now and you're paying later and you're paying extra and
you're paying basically an interest charge, yes, that's known as ריבית. ribbis.
That's exactly what it is. They're lending you the money and they're
charging you interest.
Okay, so now let's continue. אמר ליה רב פפא לרבא. Amar lei
Rav Pappa l'Rava. What?
I mean, if you pay your credit cards there's no interest, right.
But if people who need to pay it and they're paying the
minimum each month, that's interest.
Sure, of course it is. Right. How does it work in Israel
when everybody is Jewish? Yeah, it's a good question, you know. Do
you do things through היתר עסקה? heter iska? How do you put
money in a bank and then they pay you... I mean now
you don't get anything for putting money in a bank but whatever,
okay? All those are interest questions. Sure, absolutely. Now you're realizing how
difficult this is in a commercial society. Okay. All right, let's go
on. הגמרא ha-Gemara says like this: אמרו ליה רבנן לרבא amru leh
rabbanan le-Rava but actually appropriately here we see that they would have
an hard time with it even there. אמרו ליה רבנן לרבא, amru
leh rabbanan le-Rava, the Rabbis said to Rava: קאכיל מר ריבית, ka-akhil
mar ribbis, you, the master, seems like you are eating ribbis, like
you're taking ribbis. דכולי עלמא שקלי ארבע ומסלקי להו בניסן. de-khulei alma
shakli arba u-maslaki le-hu be-Nisan. Everybody else who owns fields they and
they rent out their fields to these sharecroppers, although here the point
is it's a rental fee, it's not a percentage fee, okay, they
take four dollars per acre and they kick their sharecroppers off in
ניסן. Nisan. מר נטר עד אייר ושקיל שיתא. mar natar ad Iyar
u-shakil shita. You basically wait until אייר, Iyar, you give them another
month, and you're taking six dollars for your rental fee. So again
it seems like because you waited a month in order to collect
your rental fee, you're taking a higher rental fee. So he said
no. אמר להו אתון קא עבדתון שלא כדין. amar le-hu attun ka
avdatun shelo ke-din. No, I'm not doing something wrong, you're doing something
wrong. Okay, not in a ריבית ribbis sense, but you're doing something
wrong. Why? ארעא לאריסא משתעבדא. ara le-arisa mishta'abeda. The land is under
the... you know, rights, like the jurisdiction, thank you, of the sharecropper.
He has a right to be on the land. What are you
doing kicking him off early? Okay? אי אתון מסלקי להו בניסן מפסידתו
להו בכמה. ei attun mesalki le-hu be-Nisan mafsidtu le-hu be-khamma. When you
kick him off on ניסן, Nisan,
you're making him lose a profit because, you know, the grain isn't
fully ready to be harvested then. So you're actually taking advantage by
kicking him off early. אנא נטרנא להו עד אייר ומבכנא להו בכמה.
ana natarna le-hu ad Iyar u-mavkhana le-hu be-khamma. I let them wait
there until אייר Iyar and he's making a bigger money because he
gets a bigger harvest because he waited to אייר. Iyar. And that's
why I charge more because because he got more. Well first he
didn't even understand to begin with. He was there an extra month,
there's an extra month's rent. Right, but I didn't even understand that
הוה אמינא, hava amina, maybe it was disproportionate, I don't know. But
the bottom line that Rava is saying is that he's getting a
lot more out of this deal so that's why he's paying me
more. It's not because I'm postponing payment. Okay. רב מרי בר רחל.
Rav Mari bar Rachel. Now רב מרי בר רחל Rav Mari bar
Rachel
who was actually, if you just look at רש"י, Rashi, fascinating רש"י.
Rashi. בת שמואל הויא. bat Shmuel havya. So this, why we have
somebody named after mother? Right? It's a... you know, it's a patriarchy.
So because he was the daughter... because it says this רבת שמואל
הויא ואישתבאי. rabat Shmuel havya ve-ishtabai. This רחל Rachel was שמואל's Shmuel's
daughter and she was taken captive. ונסבה עובד כוכבים. u-nesava oved kokhavim.
And then she was married by a non-Jew in captivity. I don't
know if it was married first or raped first or whatever. But
anyway, ונתגייר. ve-nitgayyer. And then he converted. ושמיה איסור גיורא. u-shmey Issur
Giyyora.
And his name was איסור גיורא, Issur Giyyora, this גר. ger. Okay,
so this רב מרי בר רחל, Rav Mari bar Rachel, his mother
was רחל, Rachel, שמואל's Shmuel's daughter, and his father was a non-Jew
who had converted, איסור גיורא. Issur Giyyora. An appropriate name for a
גר. ger. רב מרי הורתו שלא בקדושה ולידתו בקדושה. Rav Mari horato
shelo bi-kdusha ve-leidato bi-kdusha. Okay, so he was conceived
before the father converted and he was born after the father converted.
ומחמת כבודו לא קרו ליה על שמיה דאבוה. u-mekhamat kevodo lo karu
leh al shmey de-avuha. And in order to... like they didn't want
to name him after, I guess, his non-Jewish father because when he
was conceived the father was still not Jewish, so he was named
after his mother. Okay, fascinating little story. Anyway, רב מרי בר רחל
Rav Mari bar Rachel and איסור גיורא, Issur Giyyora, his father, come
up a number of times in ש"ס. Shas. רב מרי בר רחל
אמשכניה ההוא נכרי ביתא. Rav Mari bar Rachel amshakhne leh hahu nokhri
beita.
So a certain non-Jew gave into...
gave to him as collateral his house. Okay, he lent money to
a non-Jew and he took the house as collateral and he was
living in the house, which was his obviously his interest payment which
he was allowed to get from a non-Jew. הדר זבנה לרבא. hadar
zabna le-Rava. And then this non-Jew sold it to רבא Rava while
it was under the control of רב מרי בר רחל, Rav Mari
bar Rachel, which raises interesting questions. If I've rented a house to
somebody can I transfer title to a different person while somebody else
is there as a... you know, as a rental? So the answer
is yes, I mean it happens all the time. But anyway, that's
what he did. Okay, he sold this... this non-Jew sold the house
to
רבא. Rava. נטר תריסר
ירחי שתא. natar taresar yarkhei sheta.
So רב מרי בר רחל Rav Mari bar Rachel waited twelve months.
שקיל אגר ביתא אמטי ליה לרבא. shakil agar beita amti leh le-Rava.
And then he took the rent and he brought it to רבא.
Rava. So for a year he lived in it rent-free but then
afterwards he decided now I have to start paying רבא Rava rent.
Why did he decide that? אמר ליה האי דלא אמטי ליה למר
אגר ביתא עד האידנא. amar leh hai de-la amti leh le-mar agar
beita ad haidanna. Why have I not paid you rent for this
last year? דסתמא... de-stama... דסתמא משכנתא שתא. d'stama mashkanta shatta.
If you remember from earlier גמרא, Gemara, it says a סתמא משכון,
stama mashkon, right when you’re sort of dwelling in a field or
a house as collateral, you have one year that the owner cannot
kick you off with for, okay? So I had one year of
rights to living in it and that was essentially my effectively my
interest payment, it was with a non-Jew. Okay, if it was with
a Jew you probably would do some nominal reduction in the loan.
Anyway, I had a year that I had total control over, total
rights, he could not have kicked me off. So that was my
rent-free year, so I wasn't gonna pay him and I wasn't gonna
pay you. Okay? When he sold the field to you, I didn't
lose my rights for that year of total control. אי בעי לסלוקיה
לא הוה מצי לסלוקיה. ei bei l'salukei lo hava matzi l'salukei.
So if he wanted to kick me off, he couldn't during that
year. So just because he sold you the house, I still had
rights to that year. I didn't pay you for that year. השתא,
Hashta,
but now, if the non-Jew were to try to kick me off,
if the non-Jew were to pay up my loan, he'd be able
to kick me off. So in this way my rights are not
total, are not total here. So now it more is really it's
your field now. And now because it's your field now and you
have fundamentally the rights to it, it's not like before when if
he can't kick me off then I own it effectively. Now that
I could be kicked off if the loan is paid, effectively I
don't own it, I'm squatting on somebody else's land. It's now your
land. For me to live on it rent-free would be a type
of a ריבית. ribbis. Now, it's not exactly a ריבית ribbis because
because he's getting a benefit from רבא, Rava, it's רבא's Rava land.
So he's getting a benefit from רבא Rava for a loan that
he owes the non-Jew. Right? You sort of see what's happening? So
he's getting money for his loan but not from the person he
owes the money to, who owes the money to him. So technically
it's okay. You might remember we had that before in the גמרא,
Gemara, somebody else to pay me for lending money to somebody else.
Okay? But it didn't look good. It doesn't look good that I'm
dwelling on this land that is owned by רבא Rava and I
have rights to dwell on it because money that I have out
that's owed to me. So therefore now, רבא, Rava, I'm going to
start paying you because it's because it's not looking good at this
stage.
Okay? And the non-Jew who owns the house is the debtor?
The non-Jew who doesn't own it anymore, the non-Jew who
he was, he's the debtor.
He was, he's the debtor. The creditor is living in the house.
Exactly. So now, לישקול מר אגר ביתא. lishkol mar agar bayta. אמר
ליה, Amar lei, he said רבא Rava back to him, אי הוה
ידענא דהוה ממושכן ליה למר לא הוה זבנינא ליה. ei hava yadana
d'hava memashken lei l'mar lo hava zavnina lei. First of all, had
I known that it was under your control, I never would have
bought it out from under you. Okay? I shouldn't have I wouldn't
have interfered with this whole setup. השתא כדיניהם עבדינא לך. Hashta kedineihem
avdina lach.
Now I'm not going to treat you differently since you sort of
inherited this relationship you had with this non-Jew, I'm going to follow
for this purposes the non-Jewish law. What would the non-Jewish law be?
כל אימת דלא מסלקנא לך בזוזי לא שקילנא אגר ביתא. kol eimas
d'lo misalkana lach b'zuzei lo shakilna agar bayta. So the same way,
or it's not so much the non-Jewish law, but it's also what
the law, what the reality would have been prior to him selling
it to me. So prior to him selling it to me,
he could not have kicked you off the land without paying up
your debt. So אנא נמי לא שקילנא מינך אגר ביתא עד דמסלקנא
לך בזוזי. ana nami lo shakilna minach agar bayta ad d'misalkana lach
b'zuzei. So here too, until the debt is paid off, it sounds
like רבא Rava says until I pay off the debt, but רש"י
Rashi says it means until I can get the non-Jew to pay
off the debt, right? Until the debt is paid off, I refuse
to accept rent from you. Okay, look at this, everybody's being a
צדיק. tzaddik. Take it! No, I'm not gonna take it! Okay, anyway,
so on the one hand it wasn't ריבית ribbis because it wasn't
being effectively taken from רבא Rava for a loan that was owed
to him by the non-Jew. And רבא Rava refused to accept it.
He said, you have that right based on your loan with the
non-Jew, you have the right to continue living in that. I'm not
I'm not going to take this from you. You know, once the
loan is paid off, then I will go ahead and take back
the land. Otherwise, I'm not going to interfere with the rights that
you have.
Right, right, right. So in the meantime, רב מרי Rav Mari who
is the creditor is living in this house, and
the house is the
משכון mashkon for the loan. Right. Yep. So at what point does
he actually gain title to the house because it's if he defaults
on the loan, the non-Jew defaults on the loan?
So at what point does I don't know. I mean, I don't
know if there's an exact, you know, that's a good question. Like,
you know, when is it
considered to be
the רבא Rava owns the house. Right, when is it considered to
be that the loan is defaulted? Like that I don't know. But
he would not be able, at this stage, he would not be
able to seize it because it's well, he would because it would
he has a lien. Yeah, you're right. You're right. So I don't
know what, when it would be considered that the loan expired. That
would be the point. Right, correct. אמר ליה רבא מברניש לרב אשי.
Amar lei Rava miBarnish l'Rav Ashi. So רבא מברניש Rava miBarnish said
to רב אשי. Rav Ashi. חזי מר רבנן דקא אכלי ריביתא. Chazi
mar rabanan d'ka achli ribis. You should look, the rabbis are eating
ריבית. ribbis. יהבי זוזי אחמרא בתשרי ומשחלי ליה בטבת. Yahavi zuzei achamra
b'Tishrei u'meshachali lei b'Teves. They give money for the wine in תשרי
Tishrei and they only select which wine they're going to take in
טבת. Teves. In between תשרי Tishrei and טבת, Teves, some wine would
turn sour, another one would be clear was good wine. So effectively
because they are not taking possession right away, so that's seen as
a loan to the wine seller. The wine seller's able to hold
onto his wine longer. So they're not taking possession right away, so
the fee that they get for letting the wine seller hold onto
his wine is they get the right to select which wines they
want to take. Okay? So that's a type of... For a ריבית,
ribbit, they're getting to choose the better wine. אמר ליה amar lei
said back to him, אינהו נמי אחמר קיהבי, אחלא לא קיהבי. inhu
nami achamar kayahavi, achala lo kayahavi. No, no, no. When they pay
for wine, a barrel of wine, they're paying for wine, not for
vinegar. Okay? So מעיקרא דחמר חמר דחלא חלא. me'ikara dechamar chamar dechala
chala. Even when they bought it, it's not like the wine changed.
It's not like you paid me for the rate of, you know,
of grape, of grapes and I delivered wine. Okay? They paid for
the rate of wine and they wanted wine, not vinegar. Okay? And
at that moment, this is the claim, it was already the quality
the wine was already going to determine which wine would stay good
and which wine would turn to vinegar. So,
so it's really like a type of a ברירה, breira, right? They
paid for wine, they paid for the proper rate of wine at
that time. Now three months later some of the wine has become
vinegar, well clearly that's not the one that they bought because, you
know, because they were only buying wine, they weren't buying vinegar. And
don't say maybe it was one they bought and it turned bad.
The claim is is that the if wine turns to vinegar three
months from now, it was already had that quality in it, it
was that inferior wine. Right. But not that it just was one
because it was going to because it was by freak became vinegar.
The claim is that it was always three months ago it has
the quality was always the wine that was going to become vinegar.
And therefore that was never the wine that they wanted to buy.
Okay? ההיא שעתא הוא דקמיבחרי, hahi sha'ata hu dekamivchari, it's just determined
at this time but it's a type of a ברירה. breira. Now
of course the point is even if all of that is true,
they still get a benefit because if I go ahead and I
buy wine here, you know, from Charlie and three months from now
it turns bad I can't say, "Oh, you know, ברירה breira איגלאי
מילתא iglai milta that it was a מקח טעות, mekach taut, give
me my money back." Okay? You're always, you know, even if it's
true that it had those qualities three months from now, you're always
taking a certain element of risk. And presumably the price factors in
that element of risk. So the fact that they are being saved
from that risk is still a benefit that they are receiving. Okay?
ההיא שעתא הוא דקמיבחרי
hahi
sha'ata
hu dekamivchari means at that time this is the one that he
chose.
Yeah, and at that time it's got determined which was the good
wine all along. Okay? But the point is that might very well
be true, but nevertheless you're getting the right to determine this and
a normal purchaser would be stuck with what he got, right? If
a normal purchaser could say מקח טעות mekach taut and get his
money back then fine, but normal anyways fine. All right, but that
was the claim. The claim was it wasn't a real benefit, it
was really just determining which was the thing that they bought.
רבינא הוה יהיב זוזי לבני אקרא דשנוותא. Ravina hava yahiv zuzei livnei
akra deshanvata. Ravina would give money to these people that lived by
this river, by these plots of land by this river called Shanvata.
ושפכי ליה טפי כופייזא. veshafchi lei tefei kufisa. And they when they
paid came time to pay him up, okay, because you know at
the end of the harvest or whatever they would, you know, he
pre-bought the grain like the thing we've been talking about, and when
it came time to give him the grain, they threw in a
little bit extra, they poured a little extra into his bag. Okay?
So, you know, a baker's dozen, right? Okay? But again, it was
later delivery of the product and they gave him a little extra
for it. Okay? So אזל לקמיה דרב אשי. azal lekamei deRav Ashi.
He went before Rav Ashi. אמר ליה, amar lei, "מי שרי? mi
sharei? Is it permissible?" אמר ליה, amar lei, "אין, in, yes. אחולי
הוא דקא מחלי גבך. achulei hu deka machli gabach. You know, yeah,
they're just giving you a gift. You know, they're מוחל mochel on
it." But of course they're מוחל mochel on it because I lent
them money. Okay? So if you take a look at תוספות Tosafot
and the you might remember other things you're not allowed to do.
If somebody lends you money, you can't rent in a house at
a discount. Remember those things? You know, you can't live in the
house for free.
All the passage of time. Right, exactly. You go into the שוק
shuk and you get some flour and they top it off with
one extra scoop.
Right, correct. So correct. The whole problem here is
the delay.
Okay, correct. That is absolutely correct. Normally somebody like we said before,
somebody wants to give you a, you know, sell you stuff more
cheaply, he wants to give you extra, that's their business if they
do it at the time of the sale. But if they're doing
it later, it's a type of a ריבית. ribbit. Okay, so if
you look at תוספות, Tosafot, ושפכי ליה טפי, veshafchi lei tefei, he
says אין זה ריבית גמורה. ein zeh ribbit gemurah. So fine, they're
giving him something. Why don't you just call it postponed ריבית, ribbit,
meaning it wasn't factored into the debt? After after the debt is
over though, I'm giving you a, I'm doing a favor for you
because you lent me money. So he says שלא היו מזכירים שנותנים
בשביל מעותיו שהיו בטלים אצלם כדפירש בקונטרס. shelo hayu mazkirim shenotnim bishvil
me'otav shehayu beteilim etzlam kidefairash bekontres. So number one he says that
they didn't mention, "Oh, thank you so much for, you know, for
paying us early before the grain was due. Here's a little gift.
Little something." If they didn't say that. They just said, "Here's the
here's the grain you ordered and we're throwing in a little extra."
So they didn't mention that it was in context of the ריבית.
ribbit. So that's important. Once you lent me money, you lent me
money a year ago, right? That's the question תוספות Tosafot asked before,
"Does that mean I can no never do you any favors now
because it'll be looked as postponed ריבית?" ribbit? So the first key
is if it's not put explicitly made in that framework, it's not
a problem. And then he says ולא דמי להלוהו ודר בחצירו שצריך
להעלות לו שכר. velo dami lehalevehu vadar bechatzeiro shetzarich leha'alot lo sachar.
If I lent you money, I can't live in your house for
free. And remember the גמרא Gemara said there even if you wouldn't
charge other people, I can't live in your house. for free, so
why is that different? Nobody explicitly said anything about the loan at
that moment, אף על פי שאינו אומר שידור בשביל ביטול מעותיו, af
al pi she'aino omer she'yeidar b'shil bi tul ma'osav, דשאני התם שעדיין
חייב לו, deshani hasham she'adayan chayav lo, because there the loan is
still active, you still owe me the money. Okay, so this becomes
really important questions, right? When are favors considered רבית? ribbis? So the
big thing תוספות Tosfos says is here there are two characteristics. Number
one, the debt is over. It's not still during the period of
the debt. They've delivered the grain. Okay, so now does that mean
for the rest of our lives I can't do you any favors?
So תוספות Tosfos says as long... you can do a favor, just
don't frame it that it's because of the money that was lent.
I am so appreciative of that time five years ago when I
was so hard up and you lent me that ten thousand dollars
I needed, I want to give you a gift. Right? That's not
okay. Okay, but here nothing is said and the loan is over,
even though it's immediately juxtaposed and, you know, clearly seems to be
in the context of that, but since the loan is over and
nothing is being said, it's okay.
That's interesting, so wait, if you don't mention it and the loan
is over, it would be better to wait a little bit time
so no one would make the association.
Yeah, but you don't have to. That's the חידוש, chiddush, right.
Yeah, but you're saying
if it's over and you don't make the literal connection.
Right. I'm coming to deliver the grain. If I were to say,
"Thank you so much for waiting the two months," or, "Thank you
so much for paying up front, here's a little gift," that's רבית.
ribbis. If I just say, "Here's the grain you ordered, and here's
a little extra just for you, take a little something home for
the wife," okay, that's not רבית. ribbis.
Okay, it might be illegal, not in this, not in this context,
but like saying, you know, lobbyists or something.
Oh, that's a different story.
Still, it might be illegal, but it wouldn't be considered...
right, right, right, that's a totally different story, but it's not רבית.
ribbis. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay. Okay.
אמר ליה. Amar lei. Now, this becomes
fascinating, because now we get to turn to issues that a little
bit touch on רבית, ribbis, but this is a very important גמרא
Gemara for other discussions as you'll see in a minute. אמר ליה
הארעא לאו דידהו היא. Amar lei ha'ara lav didhu hi. So he
just all of a sudden decided that there's a new problem. One...
I mean, I don't know why he didn't ask this beforehand: How
can I even accept delivery of their grain? Maybe he just discovered
it. It turns out it wasn't even their land. It turns out,
as we're going to see in a minute, that they were seizing
or using lands of people that had defaulted on their taxes to
the government. So maybe I shouldn't even be able to take the
grain altogether, forget any רבית ribbis discussion. Yeah, why not? Because it's
stolen property. They're using... they're growing the grain on property that isn't
theirs.
So the whole land is expropriated?
Right, right. I mean, we'll see what's going to happen. אמר ליה,
Amar lei, he said to him, ארעא לטסקא משעבדא. ara l'taska meshabda.
The land is subjugated to the... to the taxes, meaning the, you
know, because of the taxes the government has rights to the land.
And therefore, ומלכא אמר, u'malka amar, and the king says, מאן דיהיב
טסקא ליכול
ארעא, man d'yahiv taska leichol ara, whoever's willing to pay the tax
can benefit from the land. Okay, and therefore they have a right
to be using the land. That's the... what the king says. Now,
this is very relevant, because this gets to a whole question of
דינא דמלכותא דינא, dina d'malchusa dina, and especially it even uses the
word מלכא, malka, the king says. So because this is the king's
law and the government law, it has implications for, you know, for
Jewish law. Why do we say, "Who the... cares what the government
says? From our הלכה, halacha, this is stolen land." No. You know,
they... this... this is the economic system we live in, you know?
And therefore, from their... their perspective, they have rights to the land
and liens to the land, and therefore they can reassign use to
the land. And... and that... that... that
economic reality, you know, is accepted within הלכה. halacha. Okay. By the
way, some ראשונים rishonim want to say or גאונים geonim want to
say that the principle of דינא דמלכותא דינא dina d'malchusa dina only
applies to a public law. I think that's the phrase: things in
which the government has interest in, not the government's law as it
affects the relationship between personal individuals. So basically, this was a governm...
a public law. It's: "If you don't pay your taxes, we have
rights to your land." Okay? We, the government, have rights to your
land. Anyway, so it's a type of... and רש״י Rashi explicitly says
here דינא דמלכותא דינא. dina d'malchusa dina. Okay, so that's why it's
okay. Now we're going to continue. The גמרא Gemara says like this.
One minute. אמר ליה רב פפא לרבא, Amar lei Rav Pappa l'Rava,
so רב פפא Rav Pappa said to רבא, Rava, חזי מר הני
רבנן דיהבי זוזי אכרגא. chazi mar hanei rabbanan d'yahvi zuzei akarga. Wait
a minute, look... look at this terrible thing. These רבנן rabbanan here...
it's so interesting, notice the רבנן, rabbanan, like the anonymous rabbis of
the ישיבה, yeshiva, are getting into these things. Anyway, these rabbis here,
they pay money to the government for the poll tax of individuals,
דאכרגא דאינש, d'akarga d'inish, ומשעבדי בהו טפי, umeshabbdi behu tfei, and then
they... some even take out the word, isn't even so much the
point, and then they
subjugate them. Meaning, Charlie here owes back taxes to the US, okay?
Or he owes poll taxes, whatever, you know, was a hundred dollars
a person. He... he has... I pay the government a hundred dollars,
and I now am going to seize Charlie and have him be
my personal valet, or have him go work in my field. Okay,
now, was he just offended that that was just taking advantage of
people? It's possible. it was also a ריבית ribbis *ribbis* issue. What's
the ריבית ribbis *ribbis* issue? Because eventually, Charlie is going to pay,
Charlie doesn't want to be in this situation forever, me making him
my personal valet, him my personal valet, so he is going to
eventually pay the government the poll tax he owes them, okay, and
I'm going to get my money back. All right, so therefore, and
then Charlie's going to be free. So what does that mean? That
means that what have I effectively done in the interim? I paid
Charlie's poll tax, three months from now he's going to pay it
up, I'm going to get my money back, or maybe he'll pay
me the hundred dollars, whatever it'll be, and then I can no
longer, no longer, you know, enslave him. So that means that basically
I have done what? I lent the hundred dollars for Charlie, I
paid Charlie's taxes for him, once Charlie reimburses me, I can no
longer use him as my slave. Okay, but until then I can,
so what am I getting for having went and forwarded Charlie the
money? I'm getting his service. Everybody here, you understand why there is
a type of a ריבית ribbis *ribbis*?
Okay, prepaid labor.
Right, I prepaid his taxes, he's going to eventually reimburse me, until
he does, I'm working him. אמר ליה *amar lei*, so how is
that acceptable? השתא איכו שכיבנא *hashta ichu schivna*, you know, he said,
oh, so good you asked me this. Had I died now, you
know, you wonder where these grandmother expressions come from, you know, I
could have died. Had I died this last moment, לא אמריתו לכו
הני מילי *lo amri lichu hani miltha*, you do not ask me
this. I can't believe that I could have died and left this
world without telling you this important הלכה halacha. *halacha*. What's the important
הלכה halacha *halacha*? הכי אמר רב Amar Rav ששת *hachi amar Rav
Sheshet*, here's what רב Rav, ששת *Rav Sheshet* says: מוהרקייא דהני *moharkayu
de-hani*, these sort of, רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says it means the like
the enslavement document of these people, of the citizens, בטפסא דמלכא מנח
*be-tapsa de-malka monach*, you know, is like
conceptually it's in the king's treasury. The same way the king fundamentally
has rights to the land, the king fundamentally is sort of like
those story with פרעה *Paroh* and יוסף *Yosef* we're going to get
to, he basically has rights to the service of the people, okay?
ומלכא אמר *u-malka amar*, and the king says: מאן דלא יהיב כרגא
לישתעבד למאן דיהיב כרגא *man de-lo yaiv karga lishhtabeid le-man de-yaiv karga*,
somebody who doesn't pay the poll tax and somebody else pays it
for him, then the king says that you have rights to that
person's service until, you know, that's the דינא דמלכותא dina d'malchusa, *dina
de-malchusa*. Okay, but again it's quite interesting because it's a דינא דמלכותא
dina d'malchusa, *dina de-malchusa*, but if it were just an issue that
how can I go ahead and enslave Charlie, you know, aren't I
stealing from him by enslaving him, you could say, okay, you're not
stealing from him, this is the law of the government that you're
entitled to, you know, but there still is an interesting question why
it's not conceptualized as ריבית ribbis *ribbis*. It might be the law
of the government, but what is the law of the government, you
know, means that I'm taking more money for a loan that I'm,
you know, not entitled to. So it's not exactly clear to me
how it gets around the ריבית ribbis. *ribbis* issue. But the bigger
point is, is that well I know this is the bigger point,
but anyway that the דינא דמלכותא dina d'malchusa. *dina de-malchusa* gives me
that right. But the important question is, this becomes the question of
when the issues of ריבית *ribbis* intersect with ritual law, like could
you say well, not issues of ריבית *ribbis*, issues of דינא דמלכותא
*dina de-malchusa*. Well, you know, this was a question that was asked
to the ראשונים *Rishonim* and some of them got apoplectic about the
that even people were asking. Let's just say דינא דמלכותא *dina de-malchusa*
would go by the government's rule of inheritance, not by the תורה
*Torah*'s law of inheritance, we'll just follow whatever the government law of
inheritance is. Okay, so you know to say oh my god, חס
ושלום *chas veshalom*, דינא דמלכותא *dina de-malchusa* only applies by דיני ממונות
*dinei mamonus*, inheritance although it's about property is still like you know
a חוק *chok* in the תורה *Torah*, it's not something that anyway
clearly you have to protect the ritual law. You don't say דינא
דמלכותא *dina de-malchusa* and we don't go by Jewish marriage, we go
by the government's definition of marriage, right? So raises an interesting question,
it might very well be that the government is entitling me to
enslave Charlie here, but still why aren't I gaining some benefit for
the fact that I forwarded him the money? Now, maybe the way
is that we're rethinking about it as a purchase. It's not that
I lent Charlie the money, I bought Charlie's the rights to Charlie's
service from the government, you know, maybe there's a way of reconceptualizing
it. But it does raise the interesting point, just saying דינא דמלכותא
*dina de-malchusa* doesn't solve the fact that there could be a ריבית
*ribbis* issue.
Okay, why wouldn't they have to pay back if they do?
Well right, so that, so it could be, so it could be
the way to understand this is, is that is that they don't
pay back, is that I work Charlie to pay off the loan
and that I am not getting any extra money for the deal.
Right, what I shared with you was one way of reading it,
that I got the work and he has to reimburse me. But
if you understand that Charlie is working off his loan, then there's
no real problem of ריבית *ribbis* and it's just a pure problem
of what entitles me to, normal הלכה halacha *halacha* wouldn't entitle me
to to enslave somebody to pay off their loan, right? We don't
have a debtor's prison, we have a גנב *ganav*'s prison, we don't
have a debtor's prison.
Okay, so isn't a עבד עברי *Eved
Ivri* a servant of a debtor? Yes, but not no, that's what
I'm saying, not normal debt, only as a result of theft. So
yeah, yeah, so you're right, one way of reading this גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* has nothing to do with ריבית *ribbis*, it just what we
don't have a debtor's prison, we don't have debtor enslavement, what allows
me to do it? And the answer what allows you to do
it is דינא דמלכותא *dina de-malchusa* and has maybe nothing to do
with the aspect of ריבית *ribbis*.
Okay, every case of עבד עברי *Eved Ivri* is a case of
theft?
exactly. Okay, but we don't have a right to seize, to enslave
somebody. Okay. Yeah, you could always sell yourself. Exactly.
Okay,
but we don't have a right to seize, to enslave somebody.
Okay.
Yeah, you could always sell yourself. Okay. Okay, let's go on. Okay,
it says like
this. Yeah, take a look תוספות. Tosfos תוספות Tosfos: is the one
that reads it as a ריבית issue. Look at תוספות: Tosfos משתעבדי
בתפי, mishtabdi bitfei, איסורא דלא גרשי טפי, issura d'lo garshi tfei, שלבסוף
היו מחזירים להם מעות הכרגא שנותנים
בעבורם. she-levisof hayu machazirim lahem ma'os hakarga she-notnim ba'avoram. They
would actually be
pay the guy back for the... וכל מה שהיו משתעבדין בהן היו
בשכר הלואה. v'chol mah shehayu mishtabdin bahen hayu bischar halva'ah. Okay, so
תוספות Tosfos. makes it a ריבית problem, but you didn't have to
read it that way, which makes the answer even more interesting according
to תוספות. All right, let's go on. The גמרא Gemara says like
this. רב סורא, Rav Sura, רב סורא רם, Rav Sura Ram, אחוי
דרבא, achui d'Rava, הוי תקיש אינשי דלא מעלי. havay takeish insha d'lo
malei. So this רב סורא, Rav Sura, רבא's Rava brother, would seize
people who were, you know, not good people like they're, I don't
know, you know, they would be, who knows, they would, you know,
maybe petty thieves or whatever they would be, people he thought were
injurious to society or something like that, ומעלי להו בגוהרקא דרבא, u'malyu
b'goharka d'Rava, and he basically put them in רבא's Rava carriage. He
sort of made them carry רבא's Rava carriage, you know, רבא's, Rava
what are those things that you carry? Palanquin? Palanquin or whatever. Okay.
The guy sitting in it. Yeah, exactly. Exactly. אפיריון. apiryon. There you
go.
So אמר ליה רבא. amar lei Rava.
So רבא Rava said, שפיר קעבדת. shappir ka'avidat. Oh, that was good.
That was acceptable. Now this is a problem because this is not
דינא דמלכותא דינא. dina d'malchusa dina. This is basically somebody that says,
we've got this guy in our village who's always engaged in shady
deals, petty theft, we've got to like we've got to, you know,
we've got to clamp down on him. We're just going to seize
him and make him the רבי's Rebbe servant or something like that.
So like who lets you do that? So says, oh, it was
good that you did that. שפיר קעבדת. shappir ka'avidat. דתניא d'tanya as
we taught, ראית שאינו נוהג כשורה. ra'isa she-eino noheig kashura. If you
see somebody acting inappropriately, מנין שאתה רשאי להשתעבד בו? minayin she-ata rashai
l'hishtabeid bo? How do you know that you can enslave him, you
know, not permanently but whatever as a type of a control, you
know, as a measure? תלמוד לומר, talmud lomar, לעולם בהם תעבודו. l'olam
bahem ta'avodu. The פסוק pasuk says, you know,
for the foreigners you can enslave them, ובאחיכם בני ישראל איש באחיו
לא תרדה בו בפרך. u'v'acheichem b'nei yisrael ish b'achiv lo tirdeh bo
b'farech.
But don't enslave your fellow Jew, don't overly, you know, oppress him,
work him too hard. So here we're going to read the פסוק
pasuk in a different way. לעולם בהם תעבודו ובאחיכם. l'olam bahem ta'avodu
u'v'acheichem.
You can enslave them and your fellow brother, you know, and your
fellow Jew. So we end the פסוק pasuk at a different place.
יכול אפילו נוהג כשורה? yachol afilu noheig kashura? Maybe you should be
allowed to do this even if they're acting properly. תלמוד לומר, talmud
lomar, no, that's the real פסוק. pasuk. ובאחיכם בני ישראל איש באחיו
לא תרדה בו בפרך. u'v'acheichem b'nei yisrael ish b'achiv lo tirdeh bo
b'farech. Okay, so anyway, so this is interesting, right? So now you're
although I said before, you only enslave people for theft or if
they sell themselves, now we find out you can enslave them for
debt if that's the or for back taxes if that's what the
government has said. And you can enslave them as a way of
control, you know, as a way of societal controls, you know, and
even if again, it's not for any debt or for anything, just
a way of a community dealing with its sort of, you know,
the undesirables of the community. אמר רב חמא. amar Rav Chama.
Now back to ריבית issues or not ריבית but whatever related. אמר
רב חמא האי מאן דיהיב זוזי לחבריה למיזבן ליה חמרא. amar Rav
Chama hai man d'yahiv zuzei l'chavrei l'mizban lei chamra. Somebody gave money
to his friend to buy wine for him. So I go to
Charlie and say, Charlie, okay, now is the time, wine is going
cheap, here's a thousand dollars, I want you to go buy me
a hundred barrels of wine, now is the good prices. Okay, and
I'm giving you some fee, here's ten dollars for your efforts. ופשע
ולא זבין ליה. u'pasha v'lo zavin lei.
And Charlie said oh ten bucks so he went and he saw
the movie, he went to see the Star Wars movie, he didn't
do it and he basically was negligent and I lost my opportunity
to buy the wine at those prices. Okay, what does Charlie owe
me? Does he owe me anything? So remember we learned all of
בבא קמא, Bava Kamma, גרמא בנזיקין פטור. grama b'nezikin patur. So his
negligence made me lose out but there was no damages. Okay, so
let's see what it says. משלם ליה כדאזלא אפרוותא דזושפט. meshaleim lei
k'ka'azla afarvata d'zushafat. So Rav said if
so he has to now pay me wine as based on the
rates that it's going at this place, wherever this big market was,
which was where the wine was being sold as the cheapest possible.
Okay, so yes, basically Charlie now even though now the prices are
higher, okay, Charlie because of his negligence made me lose out, he
has to give me the deal that I would have gotten at
the best rates that I would have gotten. So okay, so this
has nothing to do with ריבית. I didn't lend him any money.
Okay, so the question is, why does he have to do it
to me? You know,
there's no damages. It's lost opportunity, it was negligence, it was גרמא.
grama. Why does he have to do this? So the גמרא Gemara
says אמר מימר אמריתה לשמעתא קמיה דרב זביד amar Meimar amritah l'shma'ata
kmaih d'Rav Zevid מנהרדעא. mi-Neharde'a. ואמר v'amar
he said, הני מילי ביין סתם. hani mili b'yayin stam.
That's only by standard wine. Not general, I should say, if I
just say Charlie, go buy wine. Or ביין זה *b'yayin zeh*, if
I say Charlie, you know, I want you to go buy Glorious
Wine, she has the best wine, okay, לא *lo*, then he doesn't
owe me damages. Why? Because then it wasn't so certain that he
was going to be able to do it anyway. מי יימר דמזבני
ליה ניהליה *mi yeimar d'mizabni lei nihalei*, maybe Gloria wouldn't have sold
him the wine. So therefore in a case where I couldn't have
been certain that, you know, there wasn't like a certain gain for
me, a certain result to rely upon, then Charlie's negligence is not
so bad. I mean it's bad, but like it's not actionable. Okay,
he doesn't owe me money. Because he could have said, you know,
who says you would have gotten the wine anyway, even if I
had done my job? Okay, but when I just say buy wine
and everybody is selling wine, I definitely would have gotten it and
he clearly made me lose out that opportunity, then we do have,
then he does have to pay. ורב אשי אמר *V'Rav Ashi amar*,
אפילו יין סתם נמי *afillu yayan stam nami*, no, even if I
just said סתם *stam* buy wine, he doesn't have to pay me.
Why? מאי טעמא *mai ta'ama*? אסמכתא asmachta, היא *asmachta hi*, because this
idea that there's an implicit understanding, or maybe explicit, that he'll have
to reimburse me if he's negligent,
that's only an אסמכתא asmachta *asmachta*, right? That's agreeing to a type
of a fine and a payment, not based on a sale, not
based on, you know, a rental, not based on whatever, it's a
penalty payment, okay. So things like penalty payments, if I don't do
my job I will reimburse you for the loss, okay, that's like
a type of a contractual arrangement based on something which I might
not be seriously wanting to commit to or don't expect will happen,
and there's not really like there's no exchange, there's no rental, there's
no whatever, it's a penalty clause that that usually is called an
אסמכתא *asmachta*, something that you don't have real commitment to obligate yourself
in, and therefore it's not binding. ואסמכתא לא קניא *V'asmachta lo kanya*,
it's not binding. So here we understand the reason Charlie would pay
me is not because of damages. Damages, it's just lost opportunity and
גרמא בנזיקין *gramma b'nezikin*. The reason Charlie would pay me is that
there's an implicit understanding when I give him this job that there's
like a penalty clause if he doesn't do the job and due
to negligence that he's going to make me make me whole, he's
going to sort of, you know, make it good. Okay, and the
question is, is that implicit penalty clause something that really is binding
or not? Because maybe, you know, he doesn't expect that he's going
to have to do it, he doesn't really want to do it,
so that's the issue of אסמכתא *asmachta*.
Okay, now the question is, is the difference between פשיעה *peshia* and
גרמא בנזיקין *gramma b'nezikin* is direct or indirect?
No, פשיעה *peshia* is the fact that you didn't do your that
you shirked your responsibility, that you were negligent. גרמא *gramma* is the
question about how something happens. The difference between גרמא *gramma* and מזיק
*mazik* is direct or indirect, yeah. מזיק *mazik* is you directly caused
damage to a physical object. This is you were passive and no
object was even damaged in the end, it was just the person
lost opportunity. There's a lot of reasons here why there are no
direct damage payments. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this, ורב
אשי מאי שנא מהא דתנן *V'Rav Ashi mai shna mei'ha d'tnan*, אם
אוביר ולא אעביד אשלם במיטבא *im ovir v'lo a'avid ashalem b'meitava*, there's
a classic example about a case which is not considered to be
אסמכתא *asmachta*. I agree to work your field, I'm a sharecropper. You
get a percentage, I get a percentage. Let's say I'm lazy, okay,
so and we get nothing. All right, you get a percentage. You
know how much 40 percent of zero is? Zero. Okay, so that's
good, why should I, no, so we actually write into their sharecropping
contract, if I let this land lay fallow and don't work it,
I will pay you with the best of the crops or the
best of land. So it's a penalty clause for not doing my
duty. Okay, so that's okay, so why is that different than this?
So it says התם בידו הכא לאו בידו *hatam b'yado hacha lav
b'yado*. There it is in his hand. You are choosing to not
work the field. Okay, here
it's not in his hand. Now what does it mean it's not
in his hand? So רש"י *Rashi* says, well, maybe they won't sell
it to
you. Okay, but but what do you mean? You just said we're
talking about יין סתם *yayin stam* and everybody is selling the wine.
So it's a little bit unclear here why the whole case is
defined as not in my hand, not under my control. Tosfos just
says, well, maybe it wasn't under my control that I could have
gotten such a low price or something. Anyway, and there's also a
big discussion in תוספות *Tosafot* about whether that's the factor that matters
by אסמכתא *asmachta*. As soon as it's not in my hand, are
you going to tell me it's אסמכתא *asmachta*? So that becomes a
whole question like is gambling אסמכתא *asmachta*, right? If I make a
bet or all those types of issues. תוספות *Tosafot* actually says maybe
at the two extremes it's not אסמכתא *asmachta*. Something you totally can
control or mostly control, that's not אסמכתא *asmachta* because you assume you'll
do the job as you need to. Something that's totally out of
your control or a random bet, I put ten dollars down on
red at the roulette wheel, so I know there's no way I
can expect whatever, so I bet the money and I agree to
it knowing that it's all it's all random. Okay, I'm but that's
my understanding and I'm willing I'm willing to bet knowing that there's
not The problem is the middle case, when it's a game that's
an element of risk and an element of chance, okay, you know,
poker or something or whatever. So in those types of things I
think because I'm I'm really Well, right, meaning but
I'm not really prepared to give up the money if I lose
because I really don't think I'm gonna lose. Okay, so anyway,
so those anyway people, anyway
bottom line is that it's interesting when it's type of a mix,
okay, that's when the question is that maybe you never really meant
to give up the money because you thought you could control it
but you really can't fully control it. It's when you know you
can't or when you really can't or when you really can, those
are better cases. The middle cases are the more complicated ones. Anyway,
that's the אסמכתא issue.
Does אוויר avir mean like the late- late fallow?
Okay, okay. אמר רבא Amar Rava says רבא. Rava. Now we're finally
up to today's stuff. Okay. אמר רבא הני בי תלתא דיהבי זוזי
לחד למיזבן להו מידי. Amar Rava hani bei tlata d'yahavi zuzei l'chad
l'mizban lehu midi.
Three people give money to one person to go buy something for
them. וזבן לחד מינייהו V'zavan l'chad mineihu and he buys for one
of them and it might even mean like you know, using one
of theirs' monies. Okay, זבן לכולהו, Zavan l'kulu, it doesn't matter. Since
they all gave together, he effectively bought for all three. So he
bought some wheat or whatever they're going on some business venture, he
cannot just buy for one of those three people. He bought from
all of the monies. Okay, however, ולא אמרן אלא דלא צר וחתומי
איניש איניש לחודיה. V'la amran ela d'la tzar v'chatumi inish inish l'chudei.
That's only if the bundles of money were not sealed and signed
each person with their individual bundle of money. But if they gave
him three separate individual bundles of money, then it's clearly not a
sort of a collective here, there's three separate people asking him to
do three separate services. So in that case, אבל צר וחתומי איניש
איניש לחודיה למאן דזבן זבן ולמאן דלא זבן לא זבן. Aval tzar
v'chatumi inish inish l'chudei l'man d'zavan zavan u'l'man d'la zavan la zavan.
So if he uses person A's money to buy this wheat, it's
only- and person B's money to buy other wheat, so that's for
A and that's for B. But if the money is all thrown
together, he's always buying for the collective. Okay. Interesting. You see here
the beginnings of I think the idea of a corporation. Okay, right.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this. אמר רב פפא משמיה דרבא
האי סיטומתא. Amar Rav Pappa mishmei d'Rava hai situmta. Okay,
now the next line, if one line in the earlier גמרא Gemara
was so very extremely important for דינא דמלכותא, this line and I
mean there's so many huge issues that came up. דינא דמלכותא, אסמכתא,
this line is huge for defining קניינים, kinyanim, right? Acts that effect
change of property. So האי סיטומתא, Hai situmta, this סיטומתא. situmta. Apparently
רש"י says a סיטומתא situmta is, is I go to Charlie who
sells wine and I'm gonna buy 10 barrels of wine for my
store. Okay, and I go ahead and I can't take delivery of
all those 10 barrels right now, I can only take one barrel
at a time. I put my mark on 10 barrels. Okay, I
put my X or my mark on 10 barrels. Those are my
10 barrels. Okay, but I didn't- I didn't do משיכה. meshicha. Okay,
so he says האי סיטומתא קניא. Hai situmta kanya. That mark acquires.
Now I own those barrels. למאי
הילכתא? L'mai hilchata? For what purposes? רב חביבא Rav Chaviva אמר למיקני
ממש. amar l'miknei mamash.
I fully own them even though I didn't do a קניין. kinyan.
ורבנן V'rabanan אמרי לקבולי עליה מי שפרע. amri l'kabulei alei mi shepara.
No, no, no. It's just like giving money. It's not a full
קניין. kinyan. It's a קניין kinyan that sort of makes it a
quasi-קניין. kinyan. So now if either one of us backs out, we
get this curse, this מי שפרע mi shepara curse. Okay, but it's
not really a full קניין. kinyan. It's similar to the money. It
sort of creates a commitment to follow through. והילכתא V'hilchata לקבולי עליה
מי שפרע. l'kabulei alei mi shepara. You're right. It's only a commitment.
It's not really a full קניין. kinyan. However, ובאתרא דנהיגי למיקני ממש
קני. U'v'atra d'nahigi l'miknei mamash kani.
In a place and where the practice is that it's understood that
when you make your mark the sale is final, that's the way
the community operates, then that becomes the הלכה. halacha Then something that
is, you know, by consensus or, you know, by custom within a
particular community, the thing that defines the sale, halachically that is binding.
Okay, and this is a big idea in הלכה halacha which is,
you know, it's referred to as סיטומתא, situmta, which basically the example
everybody always gives is from the diamond industry where they say like
מזל וברכה. mazal u'vracha. So I don't know if you know this
and the מזל וברכה, mazal u'vracha, that's understood to be the deal's
final. You know, like in some places it would be like a
handshake. And like it's, you know, and within that industry it is
not understood as just like an agreement, it's like you know on
eBay they say or whatever they say, you know, bids are final
binding contracts, right? So you know, within various industries you have different
things that are treated as this is the final binding act. Okay,
and this point is that הלכה halacha recognizes that. הלכה will- so
sort of like הלכה recognizes דינא דמלכותא. The usual explanation for this
is is that you know the whole structure of קניינים kinyanim is
based on the idea often of גמירות דעת. gmar das. When I
am fully committing, you know, the act might almost be seen as
reflecting גמירות דעת, gmar das, you know, or maybe it's objectively demonstrating
ownership. But therefore I can create- we can create our own symbols
and our own acts that reflect גמירות דעת. gmar das. And when
that גמירות דעת gmar das is really present, that effects the transfer
even if it's not a קניין kinyan that הלכה has defined. It's
a little more of a do-it-yourself type of a thing. Okay, let's
keep on- let's keep on going. We're gonna make a push, we're
gonna get to the bottom of the page. ההוא תחלא לקוצרין. Hahu
tichla l'kotzrin. If the guy was with an early- got his grain
out. there early, you can buy it, buy it from him for
later delivery as long as he has the grain available. Remember, you
can pay the person if he doesn't have the grain if it's
יצא השער. yatza hasha'ar. If everybody is selling and the price is
fixed. But if he's early, an early seller, and other people are
not selling, okay, you can only pre-buy it from him if he
actually already has it in his possession. That's the basic principle. So
היו תחילה לקוצרים. Hayu techila l'kotzrin. אמר רב Rav מחוסר שתיים פוסק
Mechusar shtayim posek שלוש אינו פוסק. shalosh eino posek. You can only
buy it from him if the stuff is two
processes away from being done. But if it's more, if there's three
stages away from being completed, that's like he doesn't have it yet.
Okay. So if he has to now pluck the grapes, press them,
da da da da and he's pre-selling you the wine, okay, he
can't do that. He can only pre-sell it because there's no it's
there are too many stages removed. If only two stages is acceptable.
ושמואל אמר, u-Shmuel amar, Shmuel says no, בידי אדם, b'yedei adam, this
ties back to the to the אסמכתא issue, בידי אדם אפילו מאה
פוסק. b'yedei adam afilu me'ah posek. If it's only missing processes that
are all under human control, then there could be a hundred processes.
I can totally control the process and I can sell to you
even though I've got, you know, a lot of work to do
to get it there, it's a total process that I'm controlling. Okay.
So it's like I do have the product already, I will get
you that product. Okay, but בידי שמיים אפילו אחת אינו פוסק. b'yedei
shamayim afilu achat eino posek. But if it's something that relies on
something in God's hands, then I you know, yes, as soon as
the next rain comes I'll be able to harvest and sell it
to you. Well, great, you don't know when that next rain is
gonna come and it might come too late. So if it's something
that depends on God, even one thing is not enough. Oh,
that's an interesting question. I like it seems like we go by
Rav, I like Shmuel's approach much better, you know. Okay. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says like this. Now we're going to see how
this works out in our משנה Mishna because our משנה Mishna describes
cases of things that seem to be a number of steps removed
from the state they have to be in for delivery. So the
גמרא Gemara says like this, תנן, Tnan, the משנה Mishna says פוסק
עמו על הגדיש, posek imo al ha-gadish, you can make the arrangement
when it's a bundle of wheat. So the גמרא Gemara says, but
you don't deliver a bundle of wheat, you deliver grain. והא מחוסר,
v'ha mechusar, it's lacking משטחא בחמה, misht'cha b'chamah, drying it out in
the sun, למבש, l'mevesh, to dry it out, ולמדש, u-l'midash,
and the actual drying it out, first you put it in the
sun, then it dries out, then you thresh it, then ומדרא, u-midra,
and then what's
ומדרא? u-midra? Oh, and then you winnow it. Okay, so those are
four steps. So the גמרא Gemara says, or three I guess. So
the גמרא Gemara says כגון דשדיא בחמה ויבש. kegon d'shadya b'chama v'yavesh.
It's already dried out. So now we're only left with two steps.
Okay, that works for Rav now. The two steps are threshing and
winnowing. So the גמרא Gemara says ולשמואל דאמר בידי שמיים אפילו אחת
אינו פוסק. u-l'Shmuel d'amar b'yedei shamayim afilu achat eino posek. Now according
to Shmuel that says that if it depends on something in God's
control, then even one step is too far removed. והא מחוסר מדרא,
v'ha mechusar midra, דבידי שמיים
היא? d'biyedei shamayim hi? How about the winnowing? That relies on God,
it relies on there being a prop an appropriate type of a
wind. So you have so that's too far removed, how can you
pre-sell it? No, אפשר בנפוותא, efshar b'nafavata, you can use a sieve.
You can do it with a it won't be as efficient if
there's not a good wind but you can still do it. Okay.
And that right, ועל העביט של ענבים, v'al ha-avit shel anavim, and
on a whatever, a barrel of grapes, okay, that you're selling the
wine while they're still in the stage of being in a barrel
of grapes. והא מחוסר, v'ha mechusar,
but one minute, it's lacking מכמר, michmar, like, you know, heating up
the grapes or apparently is what they used to do ועילוי לבי
מעצרתא, v'iulay l'bei matzarta,
and bring it to the threshing floor, למידש, l'midash, then the threshing
of it, ולמנגד, u-l'migad, and the wine then running into the pit.
So that's a lot of steps. So it says כדתני רב חייא
על הכומר של זיתים. k'di'tni Rav Chiyya al ha-komar shel zeitim. When
we're going to get to the issue of olives, he says he
uses the word כומר, komar, which is a word that refers to
a type of a vessel that it was in after it was
sort of like heated up. הכא נמי על הכומר של ענבים. hacha
nami al ha-komar shel anavim. Here too it's in this vessel where
it's heated up. So apparently this heating up thing was not that's
what מכמר michmar refers to. So the גמרא Gemara says nevertheless, והא
מחוסר תלת, v'ha mechusar tlat,
but there are three things still: bringing it to the threshing floor,
thresh or not to the to the pressing floor, pressing it, and
then having it run into the pit. So the גמרא Gemara says
no, באתרא דזבין הוא דנגיד. b'atra d'zavin hu d'nagid. At the place
where the guy who buys the wine, he's the one that does
that final step of having it flow into the pit. To me
that seems a little bit hard to believe. You're buying wine and
they say, "Oh, you bought the wine, you'll have to come on
this and this day when we're doing the threshing and you'll have
to do the final step." Like whatever. But that's the way the
גמרא Gemara gets out of saying that there are three steps removed.
ועל המעטן של זיתים, v'al ha-ma'atan shel zeitim, this other type of
a vessel filled with olives. But what you're buying is not the
olives, you're buying the olive oil. Okay, that wasn't clear at least
it wasn't clear to me in the משנה, Mishna, but that's what
the גמרא's Gemara assuming. So והא מחוסר, v'ha mechusar, one minute, it's
lacking מכמר, michmar, also this heating up process, ועילוי לבי דאפי, v'iulay
l'bei dapi, bringing it to the pressing floor, למידש, l'midash, then pressing
it, ולמנגד, u-l'migad, and having it flow just like the wine. So
תני רב חייא על הכומר של זיתים. tni Rav Chiyya al ha-komar
shel zeitim. So he has the word the קומר komer of זיתים,
zeitim, which is the dish it's in after it's warmed up, so
that eliminates one of the processes. So but fine, we're down from
four to three. So the גמרא Gemara says האיכא תלת, ha'ika telat,
but there's still three processes, you know, there's the bringing it, the
pressing of it, and the running and the and then the extracting
of the oil. ואזדו לטעמיה דאיהו דזבין הוא דמנגיד, ve'azdu leta'amei de'ihu
dezavin hu demangid, same story, the guy who buys the oil, he's
the one that actually does the final step of the process, which
is again quite hard to believe. Okay. ועל הביצים של יוצר. ve'al
habeytzim shel yotzer. Now you buy it on these balls of clay.
Okay, but apparently you're not buying the clay. Again, I don't think
I explained it this way, the משנה Mishnah wasn't clear to me.
You're not buying the clay, you're actually buying the pot. But it's
only in the stage right now as a ball of clay. So
the גמרא Gemara says אמאי והא מחוסר ליפופי, amai veha mechusar lipufei,
it's lacking sort of the flapping that you do on it, you
know, to get it whatever. ויבושי veyivushei and the drying out of
it. ועייולי לאתונה ve'ayulei le'atuna
and putting it into the what do you call to the oven.
למשרף lemishraf in order and then firing it, ולמיפק ulemifak and taking
it out of the oven. That's a lot of steps. כגון דמלפפא
ויבושא. kegon demelafefa veyivusha.
It's already been shaped and dried, and all it now requires, and
somehow it's still called a lump of clay even though it's really
an unfired vessel. All it requires now is being put in the
oven. So the גמרא Gemara says והאיכא תלת, veha'ika telat, there's still
three steps: putting it in the oven, firing it, and taking it
out. ואזדו לטעמיה דאיהו דזבין הוא דמפיק. ve'azdu leta'amei de'ihu dezavin hu
demaphik. Now the guy who buys, he gets the special honor of
taking it out of the oven. Okay, again we're having him do
one of the steps. All of the evidence is against רב, right?
All this evidence shows that there's a lot of steps and it's
still okay to buy it even with a lot of steps to
go. It works very well for שמואל, Shmuel, because these are all
steps that are in human control, and that makes it okay to
buy it at an early stage.
This seems like a nice custom in a way, if it was
actually the custom in all these cases, if there was a society
where the person who's purchasing is involved.
Right. And that's true I guess if you're a homeowner. If you're
a businessman and you're trying to buy all this stuff, but right.
Okay. ועל הסיד מששקעו בכבשן, ve'al hasid misheshika'o bekivshan, and like plaster
after it's been like placed into the oven, whatever, in the kiln.
Okay. So apparently what you'll see is you did, you took stones,
you put it in a kiln, and then you crushed it and
you made this type of a powder. The גמרא Gemara says והא
מחוסר מקלא, veha mechusar mikla,
it's lacking being fired in the oven. ואפוקי ve'afokei taking out. ומידק
umidak and grinding it. That's three steps. ואזדו לטעמיה דאיהו דזבין הוא
דדייק. ve'azdu leta'amei de'ihu dezavin hu dedayyek. The case, the guy who
buys it, he's the guy that does the grinding. Okay. ולשמואל דאמר
בידי אדם אפילו מאה פוסק, uleshmuel de'amar bidei adam afilu me'ah posek,
according to שמואל Shmuel that says that when it's under human control
it could be a hundred steps removed and you could already buy
it. It's considered enough that the guy has it, even though it's
a hundred steps removed. למה
לי נששקעו בכבשן? lama li nishishikao bekivshan? Why does it say that
you can buy this plaster after it's been placed into the oven?
You should be able to buy it even before it's been placed
into the oven. It doesn't matter how many steps there are involved.
So the גמרא Gemara says אימא משראוי לשקעו בכבשן. eima mishedaroy leshakao
bekivshan. Fine. It means when it's at the stage where it's fit
to be put in the oven. All right. So that was an
interesting debate of רב and שמואל, Shmuel, got us through that part
of the דף daf pretty quickly. Let's do one more piece. ועל
הביצים של יוצר, ve'al habeytzim shel yotzer, back to these balls of
clay. תנו רבנן. tanu rabanan. אין פוסקין על הביצים של יוצר עד
שיעשו דברי רבי מאיר. ein poskin al habeytzim shel yotzer ad sheye'asu
divrei Rabi Meir. רבי מאיר Rabi Meir
says you cannot buy them until they are actually shaped into these
balls of clay. Okay, this gets back to the issue about, you
know, is it considered like you're in possession of them? So they
have to be made.
עד שיעשו דברי רבי מאיר. ad sheye'asu divrei Rabi Meir. אמר רבי
יוסי במה דברים אמורים בעפר לבן. amar Rabi Yosi bameh devarim amorim
be'afar lavan. When is that true? Because this is again the principle
you can only pre-buy it if the guy owns it. So he
says that idea that they have to be shaped into balls of
clay and the guy has to own it, that's by this stuff
that's made out of this white dirt, okay, which apparently was rarer
and it wasn't readily available to other people. So this guy therefore
has to own it and be in possession of it. אבל בעפר
שחור, aval be'afar shachor, black dirt, כגון כפר חנניה וחברותיה וכפר שיחין
וחברותיה, kegon Kefar Chananya vachavroteiha vechefar Shichin vachavroteiha, like are sold in
these two villages, פוסקין, poskin, you can do it even though the
guy doesn't own it yet. Why? Because it's a case like יצא
השער. yatza hasha'ar. אף על פי שאין לזה יש לזה. af al
pi she'ein lazeh yesh lazeh. Okay, so if it's something that only
few people have possession of, you've got to be in possession of.
If it's something that everybody has possession of, you can pre-sell it
even if you don't yet own it
inside the clay factory or whatever.
Right. אמימר יהיב זוזי מכי מייתו עפרא. Ameymar yahiv zuzei miki maytu
afra. Now אמימר Ameymar would pay money from the time that they
would bring the dirt in. They had not yet made it into
a lump of clay, but they would bring the dirt in. So
the גמרא Gemara says the
question: כמאן? keman? Now apparently this was the black dirt. אי כרבי
מאיר הא אמר עד שיעשו. ei keRabi Meir ha amar ad sheye'asu.
If it's like רבי מאיר, Rabi Meir, and you have the dirt,
it's only until they get made into these balls of clay, and
this is just dirt. אי כרבי יוסי אף על פי שאין לזה
יש לזה. ei keRabi Yosi af al pi she'ein lazeh yesh lazeh.
According to רבי יוסי, Rabi Yosi, if we're dealing with black dirt,
then you don't need to have it at all because other people
have it. So what is this פשרה peshara that you have to
have it but it can still be dirt? It doesn't have to
be the ball of clay yet. So the גמרא Gemara says
לעולם כרבי יוסי ובאתרא דאמימר אשיק עפרא. le'olam keRabi Yosi uv'atra de'Ameymar
ashik afra. And in the place of אמימר Ameymar dirt was rarer,
was not this type of dirt apparently, it was not so
common. So once you got the dirt in, then you're ready, then
you can rely on the fact that it'll be made into the
clay and it'll be delivered, ויהבו זוזי, v'yahavu zuzei, ודלא לא, v'd'lo
lo,
and not not. So this is one of these types of things:
which is it, is it considered like it's readily available then you
don't have to own it, if it's not readily available you have
to own it? In this case of the black dirt we're somewhere
in between. You had to have the dirt but you didn't yet
have to have it into a ball of clay. Okay, I'm just
going to go a few more minutes.
The dirt is the clay actually?
Well, yeah, but it hasn't been formed yet. I'm just going to
go just so we can turn the דף, daf, ופוסקין על הזבל
כל ימות השנה, u'poskin al ha'zevel kol yemot hashana, and you could
arrange pre-buy dung any time of the year because apparently dung is
always available even if the guy doesn't have it. So then some
say no, only during certain times, right? And then the חכמים chachamim
said no, no, no, you can do it at all times. So
the גמרא says חכמים היינו תנא קמא, Chachamim hainu Tanna Kamma, the
חכמים chachamim sound like the first opinion, the first opinion also said
the whole year. So the גמרא says אמר רבא ימות הגשמים איכא
בינייהו. Amar Rava yemot hageshamim ika beinyahu. No, the difference is the
rainy season. When some say, you know,
one stage is you can buy it at all times of the
year, even if it's the rainy season is when the dung is
not so readily available. The rainy season because the stuff becomes dung,
you know, after it rains and whatever, it gets disgusting, I don't
know the way רש״י Rashi explains it, during the rainy season. So
it's available in the summer months. Okay, so therefore, so one opinion
says the guy doesn't have to own it, but it has to
be during the summer months. The other opinion says no, he has
to own it. And the third opinion says you can even buy
dung in the rainy season because it's enough available that even though
it's not at the height of its availability, you can buy it
from somebody even if he still doesn't own it. Okay, I see
that everybody is leaving on me, nobody is willing to stay later,
so we are going to